<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Book | Weblog of Volkan Cirik]]></title>
  <link href="http://wolet.github.com/blog/categories/book/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://wolet.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-03-26T01:00:19-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://wolet.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Volkan Cirik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review: Surely You Are Joking Mr Feynman]]></title>
    <link href="http://wolet.github.com/blog/book-review-surely-you-are-joking/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-26T00:29:58-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://wolet.github.com/blog/book-review-surely-you-are-joking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my first year at Izmir High School of Science, I read “The Character of Physical Law” from Feynman. Although it was my prep year, I was able to understand the most of the book. Now that I read Feynman’s memoir, it makes sense why I was able to understand the fundamental laws of universe : he is an excellent storyteller in addition to being a great scientist. Unlike the most other writers, he does not play word games and comes to the point right away.</p>

<p>This book was so much fun to read. Yes all the stories are fun, but also, he has such a <em>clean</em> style you feel like you are having a chat with this genius.</p>

<p>The most of the book also is about his love of science and scientific integrity. I hope someday in future this book will be mandatory reading in graduate schools.</p>

<p>Here’s a list of some quotes to remember:
&gt; .. nothing at MIT had ever reminded me of my lab at home. Suddenly I realized why Princeton was getting results. They were working with the instrument. They <strong>buil</strong> the instrument; they knew where everything was, they now how everything worked …</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>.. actually, there was a certain amount of genuine quality to my guesses. I had a scheme, which I still use today when somebody is explaining something that I’m trying to understand: I keep making up examples.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>.. Von Neumann gave me an interesting idea: that you don’t have to be responsible for the world that you’re in. So I have developed a very powerful snse of social irresponsibility …</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>.. you have no responsibility to live up to what other people think you ought to accomplish. I have no responsiblity to be like they expect me to be. It’s their mistake, not my failing.</p>
</blockquote>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review: Now: The Physics of Time]]></title>
    <link href="http://wolet.github.com/blog/book-review-now-the-physics-of-time/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-19T20:55:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://wolet.github.com/blog/book-review-now-the-physics-of-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am a big fan of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_A._Muller">Richard Muller</a> because of his insightful answers on quora. He announced his book in one of the answers on quora, I even preordered it hoping it would be as good as his answers on quora. His main argument is not only space is created, time is also created. The now we experience is the latest created time in the universe. His argument could be more convincing if he used the space more wisely. The book could have been much shorter if he excluded his side stories about how his colleagues won prizes. Another annoying section is Part IV where he rants about physicalism and how and why he thinks he has a soul and free will which does not serve anything good for his argument about now. To his credit, he explains very well the hard topics of physics (e.g. relativity, quantum entanglement etc) to the layman like me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
